# JIACHENG ZHU

4 Emerson Place, Apt 912, Boston, MA 02114

(+1) 734-882-9807  $\diamond$  zjc@csail.mit.edu  $\diamond$  https://jiachengzhuml.github.io/  $\diamond$  Github

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Jiacheng Zhu's research aims to develop interpretable machine learning techniques that transport and utilize knowledge across different domains. To achieve this goal, he leverages probabilistic theory, Bayesian inference, and optimal transport. He tackles machine learning problems on heterogeneous real-world datasets in healthcare and robotics.

## RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher, MIT CSAIL, Cambridge, MA, USA Advisors: Justin Solomon, Marzyeh Ghassemi Topics: Geometric-inspired foundational models & generalizable ML for healthca	Sep 2023 - Now
Research Assistant, CMU, Pittsburgh, PA, USA Advisors: XuanLong Nguyen, Ding Zhao, Bo Li Topic: Generalizable machine learning on heterogeneous domains with optimal to	Sep 2018-Aug 2023 cransport
Research Scientist Intern, Apple AI/ML Health AI, Seattle, WA, USA Mentors: Haraldur Hallgrímsson, Shirley Ren Topic: Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) for time sequence data	May 2023-Aug 2023
Research Intern, AT&T Labs, New York, NY, USA Mentors: Aritra Guha, Zhengyi Zhou, Cheryl Brooks Topic: Statistical machine learning and algorithmic fairness	May 2022-Aug 2022
Research Scientist Intern, Apple AI/ML Health AI, Seattle, WA, USA Mentors: Greg Darnell, Shirley Ren Topic: Physiology-informed generalizable machine learning for time sequence da	<i>May 2021-Oct 2021</i> ta
Research Intern, Isuzu Technical Center of America, Ann Arbor, MI, USA Mentor: Yong Sun Topic: Domain adaptation and deep generative model for motion prediction	May 2020-Aug 2020
Quantitative Research Intern, Etiger Capital Partners, Shanghai, China Topic: Event-driven strategy based on probabilistic graphical models	May 2017-Aug 2017
EDUCATION	
M.S. in Machine Learning, Machine Learning Department School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, PA, USA	Dec 2019 - Jan 2022
Ph.D. Candidate, Mechanical Engineering College of Engineering, Carnegie Mellon University, PA, USA	Sept 2018 - Aug 2023
Minor in Data Science, School of Computer Science, Fudan University, Shanghai, China	Sept 2015 - June 2017
<b>B.Eng. in Aerospace design and Engineering</b> , School of Aeronautics and Astronautics, Fudan University, Shanghai, China	Sept 2013 - June 2017

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS & PREPRINTS

Generalizable Machine Learning

1. [Under review] Functional Optimal Transport: Map Estimation and Domain Adaptation for Functional Data,

**Jiacheng Zhu**\*, Aritra Guha\*, Dat Do\*, Mengdi Xu, XuanLong Nguyen, Ding Zhao, submitted to Journal of Machine Learning Research, under review.

2. [ICML 2023] Interpolation for Robust Learning: Data Augmentation on Wasserstein Geodesics,

Jiacheng Zhu, Jielin Qiu, Aritra Guha, Zhuolin Yang, Xuanlong Nguyen, Bo Li, Ding Zhao. PMLR International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2023.

3. [ACL 2023] Semantics-Consistent Cross-domain Summarization via Optimal Transport Alignment,

Jielin Qiu, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Mengdi Xu, Frank Dernonocourt, Trung Bui, Zhaowen Wang, Bo Li, Ding Zhao, Hailin Jin, Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) 2023.

4. [NeurIPS 2022] Curriculum Reinforcement Learning using Optimal Transport via Gradual Domain Adaptation,

Peide Huang, Mengdi Xu, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Laixi Shi, Fei Fang, Ding Zhao, Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS )2022.

5. [NeurIPS 2020] Task-Agnostic Online Reinforcement Learning with an Infinite Mixture of Gaussian Processes

Mengdi Xu, Wenhao Ding, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Zuxin Liu, Baiming Chen, Ding Zhao, *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2020)*.

6. [NeurIPS Workshop 2019] Recurrent Attentive Neural Process for Sequential Data Shenghao Qin\*, Jiacheng Zhu\*, Jimmy Qin, Wenshuo Wang, Ding Zhao, Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2019) Workshop.

## Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning for Health

7. [ICASSP 2023] Cardiac Disease Diagnosis on Imbalanced Electrocardiography Data Through Optimal Transport Augmentation,

Jielin Qiu\*, **Jiacheng Zhu**\*, Mengdi Xu, Peide Huang, Michael Rosenberg, Douglas Weber, Emerson Liu, Ding Zhao, 2023 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2023.

8. [EACL 2023] Transfer Knowledge from Natural Language to Electrocardiography: Can We Detect Cardiovascular Disease Through Language Models?,

Jielin Qiu, William Han, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Mengdi Xu, Michael Rosenberg, Emerson Liu, Douglas Weber and Ding Zhao, *The 17th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL) 2023.* 

9. [MLHC 2022] GeoECG: Data Augmentation via Wasserstein Geodesic Perturbation for Robust Electrocardiogram Prediction,

**Jiacheng Zhu**\*, Jielin Qiu\*, Zhuolin Yang, Douglas Weber, Michael Rosenberg, Emerson Liu, Bo Li, Ding Zhao, *PMLR Machine Learning for Healthcare (MLHC) 2022*.

10. [CHIL 2022] PhysioMTL: Personalizing Physiological Patterns using Optimal Transport Multi-Task Regression,

**Jiacheng Zhu**, Gregory Darnell, Agni Kumar, Ding Zhao, Bo Li, XuanLong Nguyen, Shirley You Ren, *PMLR Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (CHIL) 2022.* 

#### Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning for Autonomy

11. [CoRL 2022] Robustness Certification of Visual Perception Models via Camera Motion Smoothing,

Hanjiang Hu, Zuxin Liu, Linyi Li, **Jiacheng Zhu** Ding Zhao, *PMLR Conference on Robot Learning* (CoRL) 2022.

12. [BuilSys 2022] Re-vibe: vibration-based indoor person re-identification through cross-structure optimal transport,

Yiwen Dong, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Hae Young Noh, The 9th ACM International Conference on Systems for Energy-Efficient Buildings, Cities, and Transportation (BuildSys) 2022.

13. [ICRA 2021] Context-Aware Safe Reinforcement Learning for Non-Stationary Environments

Baiming Chen, Zuxin Liu, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Mengdi Xu, Wenhao Ding, Liang Li, Ding Zhao *The 2021 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA 2021)*.

14. [T-ITS] Spatiotemporal learning of multivehicle interaction patterns in lane-change scenarios

Chengyuan Zhang, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Wenshuo Wang, Junqiang Xi, *IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems*, 2021.

15. [ITSC 2018] A Tempt to Unify Heterogeneous Driving Databases using Traffic Primitives

**Jiacheng Zhu**, Wenshuo Wang, Ding Zhao, The 21st IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITSC) 2018.

16. [NME] A theoretical model for delayed hydride cracking velocity considering the temperature history and temperature gradients

Jingyu Zhang, **Jiacheng Zhu**, Shurong Ding, etc., Nuclear Materials and Energy 16 (2018): 95-107.

17. [SMiRT] Evaluation of the Effect of Temperature Gradient and Irradiation on Threshold Stress Intensity Factor in Delayed Hydride Cracking and Simulation on DHC Velocity for Zirconium Alloy Cladding Tubes

**Jiacheng Zhu**, Jingyu Zhang, Shurong Ding, etc. oral report, proceedings with the 19th Conference on Structural Mechanics in Reactor Technology, Beijing, China, Oct 16-18, 2016

#### ACADEMIC SERVICES

Conference reviewer International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)

Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

Artificial Intelligence and Statistics Conference (AISTATS), (2023 top re-

viewer)

Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)

Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (CHIL)

Machine Learning for Healthcare (MLHC)

Journal reviewer Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR)

Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems (T-ITS)

IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Vehicles (T-IV)

Organizer ICRA 2022 SeasonDepth Challenge

## TALKS & ACTIVITIES

Generalizing AI/ML for Autonomous Driving under Distribution Shift Oct 2022

Long talk Wayve AI, London (remote), Hosted by Vijay Badrinarayanan,

Robustify ECG Automatic diagnosis via distribution interpolation Sep 2022

Long talk Allegheny Health Network, Pittsburgh

GeoECG: Data augmentation for robust cardiovascular prediction Aug 2022
Spotlight presentation Machine Learning for Healthcare, 2022, Durham, North Carolina

PhysioMTL: Physiology-informed multi-task Learning
Spotlight presentation
Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning, 2022

Functional Optimal Transport February 2022
Spotlight presentation AAAI Workshop on Optimal Transport and Structured Data Modeling

Demographic aware multitask learning for Heart Rate Variability

August 2021

Apple AI/ML, Remote

Oxford Machine Learning Summer School

Attendee

OxML 2020, Oxford University (Online)

Recurrent Attentive Neural Process for Sequential Data

Dec 2019

Lightning talks

NeurIPS 2019, Learning with Rich Experience (LIRE) Workshop, Vancouver

Artificial Intelligence for Data Discovery and Reuse (AIDR) 2019

\*\*Long talk\*\*

\*\*Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh\*\*

### **HONORS**

- · Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning, Doctoral Symposium, 2023
- · International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) top reviewer, 2023
- · Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship, North American, 2022
- · Apple Scholars in AI/ML PhD fellowship nomination, 1 out of 3 at CMU College of Engineering, 2021
- · Certification, Oxford Machine Learning Summer School, 2020 (Online)
- · NeurIPS Student Travel Award, NeurIPS , 2019
- · Rackham Travel Grant Fellowship, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 2018
- · Junyuan Scholarship for Undergraduate Student, Fudan University, 2017
- · Outstanding Undergraduate Thesis, Fudan University, 2016
- · Xiexin Excellent Student Scholarship, Fudan University, 2016
- · Junyuan Scholarship for Undergraduate Student, Fudan University, 2016
- · 'GuangHua Innovation Prize' of Fudan University, Fudan University, 2015
- · China Graduate Future Flight Vehicle Innovation Competition, First Prize, 2014

# SELECTED COURSES

Statistical Machine Learning, Probabilistic Graphical Models, Convex Optimization, Reinforcement Learning, Advanced Deep Learning, Intro to Machine Learning, Computer Vision, Machine Learning with Large Datasets, Mobile Robotics: SLAM, Robot Kinematics & Dynamics, Database Management Systems, Data Structures and Algorithms

#### TECHNICAL AND PERSONAL SKILLS

 ${\bf Computer \ Languages} \qquad \quad {\rm Python, \ JavaScript, \ C/C++, \ MATLAB}$ 

Softwares & Tools TensorFlow, Pytorch, ROS, OpenRAVE, MySQL, OpenCV, CUDA,

Solidworks, LATEX

Languages English, Mandarin, Shanghai Dialect